Guide to the Isaac Hicks Papers 1791-1820 MS 297
New-York Historical Society
- Series II: Business Documents, 1799-1809; 16 Linear feet
  - Hicks Bill Book, 1799-1805 (Box 102)
    This book includes a list of bills that Hicks wrote or owed, primarily between 1799 and 1805. It is organized into columns stating by whom drawn, note or bill, by whom received, date, days to run, when due, and then a lists of months, where an amount is filled in under the month that the payment is due.
  - Cargo Books, Insurance Account Books, Bill Books, 1795-1797 (Box 103)
    This box contains 15 folders of cargo books, insurance account books, and bill books. In the cargo books, the pages are broken into columns and are titled: date, marks, number, quality, and crates. One is bound in burlap and the other is bound in paper. The insurance account books is predominantly a book of debits and credits based on purchasing of insurance. Columns can include the date, ships names, captain, whether the vessel or cargo was what was insured, the amount it was insured for, and the premium paid. The bill books include lists of money lent and borrowed, to whom it was lent, and when payment is due.
  - Hicks Ledger Book, 1799-1802 (Box 106)
    This is an oversized volume labeled 'I.H. Ledger B.' Inserted into the first page is a separate volume that appears to act as an index to the volume. The beginning of the volume contains bills payable and bills receivable, but a majority of the volume is ordered by individual or organization. A majority of the entries appear to be balancing other account books or paying to cash.
  - Hicks Ledger Book, 1799-1807 (Box 107)
    This box contains an oversized volume labeled "ledger book". The cover is separating from the remainder of the binding. A majority of the volume is organized date, and the pages are labeled by the individual or company discussed, and the entries are for payments to individuals or to specific accounts.
- Series III: Non-Business Documents, 1790-1850; 1 Linear feet
  This series includes non business documents including a book of donations for the African Free School, and recollections regarding Isaac Hicks after his passing. This is the smallest series, as a majority of the collection is business related.
  There is no particular arrangement to this series, as the series is so small.
  - Summary of Letters; Recollections about Isaac Hicks; Letter re Isaac Hicks as Director of Merchant's National Bank; Hicks Recollections about voyage (Box -)
    - Letters Re Isaac Hicks (Box 1, Folder 1)
      This folder contains letters regarding Isaac Hicks, written after his death. One letter is a statement from the Merchant's National Bank, stating that Hicks was a founding member and acting president of the bank for a period of time. Another letter is from Richard Motts to John W. Hicks (grandson of Isaac Hicks) and recalls meetings with Hicks when Motts was a child, as well as some recollections about the Hicks family in general.
      Also included in this folder is a sketch written by Hicks in 1792 regarding a voyage to Savannah, Georgia and the proceedings while there. This document is extremely difficult to read due to bleed-through of the ink, but some early topics include the weather at the time the ship launched, and how early on in the voyage, a large number of the passengers fell ill.
  - African Free School, Undated (Box 103, Folder 15)
    This book is in regard to the African Free School and donations towards its funding. The book is introduced with "The immediate guardians of the African Free School are induced to apply for aid in support of the institution, as the funds heretofor granted for that purpose are inadequate to the present establishment; and by contracting the plan, many youth, now in a fair way to become useful members of society, would be deprived of the inestimable privileges they now enjoy.—About one hundred & fifty children of Africans and their descendants, at present partake of the benefits of this seminary; they have no particular society to look up to for assistance, their only reliance is on the general benevolence of the citizens of New York on those philanthropic individuals, who know no stronger call on their exertions, than the conviction that those exertions will be useful to their fellow creatures." The rest of the book lists individuals, and how much they donated. Only 3 pages of the book are filled.